A Guide to the Bob Bersson Collection, 1981-2017: SC 0272
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Bob Bersson Collection
1981-2017
Special Collections, James Madison University
Robert Bersson (Bob)
SC 0272
1.22 cubic feet; 4 boxes, 3 vhs, 31 audiocassettes, 2 3.5" floppy disks
The Bob Bersson Collection, 1981-2017, are comprised of documents and media related to Bersson's work as a community activist in Harrisonburg, and professor of art at James Madison University. It contains Bersson's professional papers, material related to the Citizens for Downtown organization, Taxpayers against Golf Spending (TAGS), WMRA's "Our Little Radio Show," and images of downtown Harrisonburg and JMU Campus.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Items were donated by Bob Bersson in five separate accessions between 2014 and 2018.
Bio/Historical Note
Bob Bersson was a professor of Art at James Madison University from 1983 until his retirement in 2003. He taught modern and contemporary art history, art criticism, aesthetics, and art appreciation. He wrote two art history/art appreciation text books: "Worlds of Art," published by Mayfield in 1991, and "Responding to Art," published by McGraw-Hill in 2004. Bersson founded the Interfaith Initiative for Peace and Justice in Harrisonburg, and remains active in local interfaith activities. In 2016, Bersson served as visiting Jewish Scholar for the Center for Interfaith Engagement at Eastern Mennonite University.
Scope and Content
The collection is comprised of documents and media related to Robert Bersson's work as an art professor at JMU and community organizer in Harrisonburg, Virginia. It is arranged into four series: Citizens for Downtown (CFD) in Harrisonburg, Taxpayers against Golf Spending (TAGS), WMRA "Our Little Radio Show," and Professional Papers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series 1: Citizens for Downtown (CFD), 1989-2017
Subseries 1: Administrative Files, 1989-2017
Subseries 2: Subject Files, 1989-2017
Series 2: Taxpayers against Golf Spending (TAGS), 1992-2002
Series 3: WMRA "Our Little Radio Show," 1987-1988
Series 4: Professional Papers, 1991-2004
Related Materials
[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Common Ground Records, 1983-2000, SC 0126, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Art -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Art appreciation -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Religions -- Relations; Community organizations -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Citizens' associations -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Social action -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; James Madison University. Department of Art; James Madison University. School of Art and Art History; James Madison University. School of Art
Genre and Form Terms:
Membership lists; Reports; Letters (correspondence); Floppy Discs; Color slides; Slides (photographs); VHS; Maps (documents); Newspaper clippings
- Series 1: Citizens for Downtown, 1989–2017
  Arrangement
  Arranged into two subseries: Administrative Files, 1989-2017, arranged chronologically, and Subject Files, 1989-2017, arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Content
  The Citizens for Downtown files contain meeting minutes, correspondence, financial reports, newspaper clippings, speeches, membership information, advertisements, and slides related to the historic preservation and revitalization of downtown Harrisonburg. A summary of the history of CFD and the Blacks Run clean-up and restoration project, written by Bob Bersson, can be found in Box 1:8.
  The series contains 771 slides with images of Harrisonburg, James Madison University, Rockingham County, and other locales in Virginia and the Northeast. Specific locations include images of downtown Harrisonburg, Hillandale Park, Black's Run, Purcell Park, and JMU buildings and campus. One slide container was labelled, "Good Models for Downtown Development," and contained images of Charlottesville, Roanoke, Richmond, Alexandria, among other locales. Another slide case was labelled, JMU Architecture, 1909-2003.
  The series also contains three VHS tapes with interviews of Bersson related to Harrisonburg downtown revitalization, as well as two 3.5 inch floppy discs labelled, "Citizens for Downtown."
  - Subseries 1: Administrative Files, 1989–2017
    - Prehistory of Citizens for Downtown, 1981-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 1, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bob Bersson Notebook, 1989–1990
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 2, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 3, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 4, 1992–1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 5, 1995–2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 6, 2004, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Citizens for Downtown Narrative and Blacks Run Clean-up Narratives, 2014, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 7, undated (Box 1, Floppy SC0272-FL3-001)
    - Citizens for Downtown Documents 8, undated (Box 1, Floppy SC0272-FL3-002)
  - Subseries 2: Subject Files, 1989–2017
    - Architectural Awards, 1990-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Blacks Run Restoration Project Documents, 1989–2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Blacks Run Restoration Project Photos, ca. 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Blacks Run Restoration Project Newspaper Clippings, 1990–2017 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Fridays on the Square, 1992–2013 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gallery Walk, 1989–1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Downtown revitalization, WHSV TV, ca. 1981 (Box 1, Vhs SC0272-VHS-001)
    - Identity Crisis, WVPT, September 7, 1989 (Box 1, Vhs SC0272-VHS-002)
    - Citizens for Downtown on TV3 News, 1989 (Box 1, Vhs SC0272-VHS-003)
    - Slides of Downtown Harrisonburg, Blacks Run, and JMU campus, c. 1981-2005 (Box 4)
      Scope and Contents
      The box contains 781 slides with images taken by and compiled by Bob Bersson. The slides depict buildings in downtown Harrisonburg; the Blacks Run River area; Hillendale Park, Harrisonburg; JMU campus and buildings; Bridgewater, Dayton, Citizens for Downtown activities; and various historic districts in northern Virginia, Charlottesville, Boston, Maryland, and other locales. A complete inventory of the slides is available upon request.
- Series 2: Taxpayers Against Golf Spending (TAGS), 1992-2002
  Arranged chronologically.
  TAGS is comprised reports, memos, maps, studies, advertisements, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and audio recordings related to a campaign against the Harrisonburg City Council's plans to build a municipal golf course in the Hillandale Park in Harrisonburg. The organization eventually formed the Citizens of Harrisonburg Advocating New Government for the Electorate (CHANGE) in 2000, who endorsed three candidates for city council -- Dorn Peterson, Carolyn Frank, and Joe Fitzgerald – all of whom were elected in May 2000. Three audiocassettes contain interviews with individuals in 2002 regarding their involvement with TAGS.
  - Harrisonburg Golf Course Feasability study, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Studies and Reports by City of Harrisonburg, 1994–2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Advertisements, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Financial Analysis of Golf Course, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CHANGE Campaign Material, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CHANGE Documents, 2000–2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ben Fordney recording, May 17, 2002 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-030)
  - Warren Dillenbeck recording, May 19, 2002 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-029)
  - Carolyn Frank recording, May 27, 2002 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-031)
- Series 3: WMRA - Our Little Radio Show, 1987–1988
  The series, "Our Little Radio Show," contains documents and audio recordints related to a variety show co-founded by Bersson in 1987, and hosted at JMU. Audio cassettes with episodes of the show have been digitized and returned to Bersson.
  - Our Little Radio Show Documents, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Our Little Radio Show Documents, March 3, 1987, undated (Box SC0272-SET-001)
    Comprised of photographs of a document with a list of Our Little Radio Show programs and dates, and an image of the article, "Show Prepares for Airwaves: 'Our Little Radio Show' Runs Through its Paces," Daily News Record, March 3, 1987.
  - April '87 Fundraiser with Our Little Radio Show excerpts, April 1, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-001)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Dominion Express, Mother's Day Show, May 10, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-002)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Joyce Breeden and Steve Parks, May 17, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-003)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Nick Whitmer, Mel & Karen Lee, May 24, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-004)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Rick Richardson & Steve Edick, May 31, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-005)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Crooked Run String Band, June 7, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-006)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Klezmer, Musikante, June 14, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-007)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Klezmer, Musikante, June 14, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-008)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Belzona Blues Revue, June 21, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-009)
  - Our Little Radio Show Windfall History, June 28, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-010)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Roy Bookbinder, July 12, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-011)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Mandelay, July 19, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-012)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Wanda Hardy and the Hardy Boys, August 2, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-013)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Gary Green & Rick Harris, August 9, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-014)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Philips and Glick and George Craft, August 16, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-015)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Steve Speakman, October 4, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-016)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Reverand Billy C. Wertz (partial), October 25, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-017)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Joyce Breeden; Our Front Porch with Nancy Griffith, November 15, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-018)
  - Our Little Radio Show, Christmas Show with Boffo, December 20, 1987 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-019)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Robin and Linda Williams, January 17, 1988 (Box SC0272-SET-001)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Michael Geddes, February 7, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-020)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Cabin Fever, Valentines Day (Side A), February 14, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-021)
  - Our Little Radio Show with John D'Earth and Robert Jospe, February 21, 1988 (Box SC0272-SET-001)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Peter and Debby Hunter, February 28, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-022)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Eddie Adcock, March 6, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-023)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Joyce Breeden, Steve Parks and Two-Gun Terry, March 13, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-024)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Wanda and the White Boys, March 27, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-025)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Windfall, April 10, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-026)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Kirk Edwards, April 17, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-027)
  - Our Little Radio Show with Heartland, May 1, 1988 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0272-CS-028)
- Series 4: Professional Papers, 1991–2004
  Professional Papers contain the papers and media created by Bersson during his tenure as a professor of Art at James Madison University. There are two folders contain documents related to significant and controversial restructuring under the Carrier Administration in 1993. Files include comments made by President Carrier during a JMU Faculty Senate Meeting in October 14, 1993, as well as other articles and reports related to faculty governance and structure.
  - AAUP Committee Documents, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Senate Documents, 1993–2007 (Box 3, Folder 5)